I collaborate with bacteria.
أنا أتعاون مع البكتيريا.
And I'm about to show you
وأنا على وشك أن أعرض عليكم
some stop-motion footage that I made recently
بعض المشاهد المسرّعة التي حضّرتها
where you'll see bacteria accumulating minerals
تقوم البكتيريا فيها بمراكمة المعادن
from their environment
من محيطها
over the period of an hour.
على مدى ساعة من الزمن.
So what you're seeing here
وبالتالي ما ترونه هنا
is the bacteria metabolizing,
هو بكتيريا تقوم بعملية التمثيل الغذائي،
and as they do so
وبينما تقوم بذلك
they create an electrical charge.
تقوم بإنتاج شحنة كهربائية.
And this attracts metals
وهذا يجذب الفلزات
from their local environment.
من بيئتها المحيطة.
And these metals accumulate as minerals
وهذه الفلزات تتراكم كمعادن
on the surface of the bacteria.
على سطح البكتيريا.
One of the most pervasive problems
واحدة من أكثر المشاكل تفشياً
in the world today for people
في العالم اليوم بالنسبة للناس
is inadequate access
هي الوصول الغير كافي
to clean drinking water.
لمياه الشرب النظيفة.
And the desalination process
وعملية تحلية مياه البحر
is one where we take out salts.
هي العملية التي من خلالها نزيل الأملاح.
We can use it for drinking and agriculture.
نستطيع استخدامها للشرب والري.
Removing the salts from water --
إزالة الأملاح من المياه --
particularly seawater --
مياه البحر بالتحديد --
through reverse osmosis
عن طريق التناضح العكسي
is a critical technique
هي عملية حساسة
for countries who do not have access to clean drinking water
بالنسبة لدول لا تستطيع الوصول إلى مياه شرب نظيفة
around the globe.
حول العالم.
So seawater reverse osmosis
وبالتالي فإن التناضح العكسي لمياه البحر
is a membrane-filtration technology.
هي تقنية ترشيح الأغشية.
We take the water from the sea
نأخذ المياه من البحر
and we apply pressure.
ونطبق عليها الضغط.
And this pressure forces the seawater
فيدفع الضغط مياه البحر
through a membrane.
عبر الغشاء.
This takes energy,
وهذا يتطلب طاقةً،
producing clean water.
وينتج مياها نظيفة.
But we're also left with a concentrated salt solution, or brine.
ولكننا نحصل أيضا على محلول ملحي مركز أو أجاج.
But the process is very expensive
ولكن هذه العملية مكلفة للغاية
and it's cost-prohibitive for many countries around the globe.
وغير مجدية إقتصادياً بالنسبة للعديد من البلدان حول العالم.
And also, the brine that's produced
كما أن الأجاج الناتج
is oftentimes just pumped back out into the sea.
غالباً ما تتم فقط إعادة ضخه إلى البحر.
And this is detrimental to the local ecology
وهذا ضار بالنظام البيئي المحلي
of the sea area that it's pumped back out into.
للمنطقة البحرية التي يضخ فيها.
So I work in Singapore at the moment,
أنا أعمل في سنغافورة حاليا،
and this is a place that's really a leading place
وهي منطقة تعتبر رائدة
for desalination technology.
في تقنيات تحلية مياه البحر.
And Singapore proposes by 2060
وتحاول سنغافورة بحلول سنة 2060
to produce [900] million liters per day
إنتاج 900 مليون ليتر يومياً
of desalinated water.
من المياه المحلاة.
But this will produce an equally massive amount
ولكن هذا سينتج كذلك كميات مماثلة هائلة
of desalination brine.
من أجاج تحلية مياه البحر.
And this is where my collaboration with bacteria comes into play.
وهنا يأتي دور تنسيقي مع البكتيريا.
So what we're doing at the moment
وبالتالي ما نقوم به حاليا
is we're accumulating metals
هو مراكمة الفلزات
like calcium, potassium and magnesium
مثل الكالسيوم والبوتاسيوم والماغنزيوم
from out of desalination brine.
من خارج أجاج التحلية.
And this, in terms of magnesium
وهذا، بالنسبة للماغنزيوم
and the amount of water that I just mentioned,
ومقدار المياه التي ذكرتها للتو،
equates to a $4.5 billion
يعادل مقدار 4.5 مليار دولار
mining industry for Singapore --
من صناعة التعدين لسنغافورة --
a place that doesn't have any natural resources.
مكان حيث لا توجد أي موارد طبيعية.
So I'd like you to image a mining industry
لذلك أدعوكم إلى تخيل صناعة تعدين
in a way that one hasn't existed before;
بطريقة لم توجد من قبل؛
imagine a mining industry
تخيلوا صناعة تعدين
that doesn't mean defiling the Earth;
لا تعني تشويه الأرض؛
imagine bacteria helping us do this
تخيلوا بكتيريا تساعدنا في القيام بذلك
by accumulating and precipitating
من خلال المراكمة والترسيب
and sedimenting minerals
ورواسب المعادن
out of desalination brine.
الناتجة عن تحلية الأجاج.
And what you can see here
وما يمكن أن تروه هنا
is the beginning of an industry in a test tube,
هو بداية صناعة في أنبوب اختبار،
a mining industry that is in harmony with nature.
صناعة تعدين منسجمة مع الطبيعة.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)